Javaram Hariharan

Email: jayaramhariharan@utexas.edu Website: jayaramhariharan.com Mobile: +1-203-249-4265GitHub: github.com/elbeejay Twitter: @HariharanJay

# Research Interests

My research leverages numerical models and remote sensing data to answer questions at the intersection of civil engineering and geology. In particular I am interested in understanding how fluvial-deltaic environments will evolve under changing external conditions.

## **EDUCATION**

• The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX

PhD, Civil Engineering

May 2019 - Aug. 2022 (Expected)

• Thesis: Top to Bottom: Modeling and Analyzing River Delta Surface Morphology and Subsurface Form

MS, Civil Engineering

Aug. 2017 - May 2019

• Thesis: Quantifying the Influence of Surface Processes on Subsurface Geometry in Deltaic Environments

• University of Maryland, College Park

College Park, MD

BS, Civil and Environmental Engineering

Aug. 2011 - Dec. 2014

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

• Los Alamos National Laboratory

Los Alamos, NM

Student Intern

Civil Engineer

Jan. 2021 - Jun. 2021

• Applied graph theory methods to quantify flux partitioning error in river deltas

• Gutschick, Little & Weber P.A.

Burtonsville, MD

• Led civil engineering site design for 2 commercial land development projects

Jan. 2015 - Jul. 2017

- Provided expert testimony at Planning Board meetings and public hearings

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- [8] Steel, E., C. Paola, A. Chadwick, J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, Z. Xu, H.A. Michael, H. Brommecker, E. Hajek (under review), Reconstructing subsurface sandbody connectivity from temporal evolution of surface networks, Basin Research.
- [7] Tull, N., P. Passalacqua, H. Hassenruck-Gudipati, S. Rahman, K. Wright, J. Hariharan, & D. Mohrig (in revision), Bidirectional River-Floodplain Connectivity During Combined Pluvial-Fluvial Events, Water Resources Research.
- [6] Miltenberger, A.M, T. Mukerji, J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, & E. Nesvold (accepted pending minor revisions), A Graph-Theoretic Monte Carlo Framework for Comparing Delta Morphology, Morphodynamics, and Stratigraphy in Numerical Models and Physical Experiments, Mathematical Geosciences.
- [5] Moodie, A. J., J. Hariharan, E. Barefoot, & P. Passalacqua (2021), pyDeltaRCM: a flexible numerical delta model, Journal of Open Source Software, 6(64), 3398, https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.03398.
- [4] Xu, Z., J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, E. Steel, C. Paola, & H.A. Michael (2021), Linking the Surface and Subsurface in River Deltas - Part 2: Relating Subsurface Geometry to Groundwater Flow Behavior, Water Resources Research, 57, e2020WR029281, https://doi.org/10.1029/2020WR029281.
- [3] Hariharan, J., Z. Xu, H.A. Michael, C. Paola, E. Steel, & P. Passalacqua (2021), Linking the Surface and Subsurface in River Deltas - Part 1: Relating Surface and Subsurface Geometries, Water Resources Research, 57, e2020WR029282, https://doi.org/10.1029/2020WR029282.

- [2] Schwenk, J. & J. Hariharan (2021), RivGraph: Automatic Extraction and Analysis of River and Delta Channel Network Topology, Journal of Open Source Software, 6(59), 2952, https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.02952.
- [1] Hariharan, J., K. Wright, & P. Passalacqua (2020), dorado: A Python package for simulating passive particle transport in shallow-water flows, Journal of Open Source Software, 5(54), 2585, https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.02585.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE	
• The University of Texas at Austin Graduate Teaching Assistant	Austin, TX
$\circ~$ Substitute lecturer for the hydrology and stochastic hydrology courses	Fall 2019
• Teaching assistant for undergraduate hydraulic engineering course	Spring 2020
o Grader for undergraduate hydraulics and hydrology courses	Fall 2018, 2019, and 2020
ACADEMIC AND VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES	
Academic Activities	
$\circ$ <b>UT Austin:</b> Graduate and Industry Networking (GAIN) committee member	2018
$\circ$ $$ UT Austin: Environmental and Water Resources Engineering Seminar comm	mittee member 2018
• CSDMS: Interactive Teaching Material Creation	Dec. 2020
* Creator of EKT Lab: Alternative mesh generation for Landlab [link]	
$\circ$ Peer-reviewer: Computers & Geosciences; Journal of Open Source Software	2020 - Present
o Topic Editor: Journal of Open Source Software	Jun. 2021 – Present
• Volunteer Activities	
o St. David's Hospital, Austin, TX: Weekly Volunteer (3 hrs/wk)	Apr. $2019 - Apr. 2020$
Grants and Awards	
• Grants	
• NSF Supplement: INTERN Funding Opportunity (\$44,999)	FY 2020
• Awards	
o University Graduate Continuing Fellowship	2021 - 2022
$\circ~$ Trigg and Fannie E. Twichell Centennial Endowed Presidential Scholarship	2020
$\circ~$ Earnest and Agnes Gloyna Endowed Presidential Scholarship	2019
• Walter L. and Reta Mae Moore Graduate Fellowship in Water Resources	2017
<ul> <li>University of Maryland President's Scholarship</li> </ul>	2011 - 2014
SHORT COURSES	
Participant	
$\circ$ Geoscientific data analysis using UNIX and GMT $[\mathrm{UTIG}]$	2021
$\circ \   \mathbf{Earth}   \mathbf{Surface}   \mathbf{Processes}   \mathbf{Modeling}   \mathbf{Summer}   \mathbf{Institute}   [\mathbf{CSDMS}]$	2020
$\circ$ Summer Institute for Earth-Surface Dynamics [NCED]	2018
J. Hariharan - September 1, 2021	2  of  3

o Earth Surface Processes Modeling Summer Institute [CSDMS]

## SKILLS AND LICENSES

#### • Skills

- o Programming/Scripting Languages: Python, Bash, MATLAB, Julia, R, Kotlin
- o Programming Tools Git, Unix, Continuous Integration, Unit Testing
- o Engineering/Mapping: AutoCAD Civil 3D, HEC-RAS, ArcGIS/QGIS, Generic Mapping Tools
- o Office/Media: IATEX, MS Office, GIMP, Illustrator/Inkscape, IHS Kingdom, Audacity

#### • Licenses

• State of Maryland Engineer in Training (EIT)

Licence #46507

## Non-refereed Publications

- [2] Hariharan, J. (2020), py\_gee\_tools v0.1, Zenodo, http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4331356.
- [1] **Hariharan**, J. (2019), Quantifying the Influence of Surface Processes on Subsurface Geometry in Deltaic Environments, M.S. Thesis, University of Texas, Austin.

#### Conference Abstracts and Presentations

- [10] Hariharan, J., K. Wright, P. Passalacqua (2021), Modeling The Influence Of Polders On River Delta Connectivity, 8th International Conference on Water and Flood Management, Abstract 100261.
- [9] Tull, N., S. Rahman, P. Passalacqua, K. Wright, J. Hariharan, H. Hassenruck-Gudipati, D. Mohrig (2020),
   Determining Local Mesh Resolution for Accurate Modeling of River-Floodplain Connectivity, 2020 AGU Fall Meeting,
   Abstract H137-003
- [8] Moodie, A. J., **J. Hariharan**, J. Caers, P. Passalacqua (2020), Constraining autogenic smaller-scale stratigraphic variability via information theoretic relationships with larger-scale observations, 2020 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP025-06
- [7] Xu, Z., J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, C. Paola, E. Steel, H. A. Michael (2019), Contaminant transport in deltaic aquifers: The impact of surface-to-subsurface connectivity, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP21D-2237
- [6] Steel, E., C. Paola, P. Passalacqua, H. A. Michael, J. Hariharan, Z. Xu (2019), Linking surface dynamics to the subsurface record: the effectiveness of overhead imagery in quantifying depositional architecture, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP21D-2236
- [5] Hariharan, J., P. Passalacqua (2019), Modeling Deltaic Evolution Amidst Anthropomorphic Development, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP23E-2261
- [4] Miltenberger, A., T. Mukerji, P. Passalacqua, J. Hariharan (2019), Comparing a Delta Numerical Model to a Flume Experiment using Monte Carlo Simulations and Graph Theory, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP31A-06
- [3] Michael, H. A., Z. Xu, J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, C. Paola, E. Steel, M. C. Perignon (2018), Surface to Subsurface Connectivity in River Deltas: From Depositional Processes to Preferential Groundwater Flow, 2018 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP42A-07.
- [2] Xu, Z., H. A. Michael, J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, C. Paola, M. C. Perignon, E. Steel (2018), Relations between static and dynamic connectivity in a deltaic aquifer, 2018 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP43D-2744.
- [1] Hariharan, J., M.C. Perignon, P. Passalacqua, Z. Xu, H. A. Michael, C. Paola, E. Steel (2018), Quantifying Connectivity Between the Surface and Subsurface in Numerically Modeled Deltas, 2018 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP43D-2746.